<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE spec PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD Specification V2.2//EN"
       "http://www.w3.org/2002/xmlspec/dtd/2.2/xmlspec.dtd" [
       ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="canonical-exi.xsl"?>
<spec w3c-doctype="rec">
    <header>
        <title>Canonical EXI</title>
        <w3c-designation>REC-exi-c14n-20180531</w3c-designation>
        <w3c-canonical>exi-c14n</w3c-canonical>
        <w3c-doctype>W3C Recommendation</w3c-doctype>
        <pubdate>
            <day>31</day>
            <month>May</month>
            <year>2018</year>
        </pubdate>
        <publoc>
            <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2018/REC-exi-c14n-20180531/">
            https://www.w3.org/TR/2018/REC-exi-c14n-20180531/</loc>
        </publoc>
        <prevlocs>
<sitem>
            <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2018/PR-exi-c14n-20180426/"
                >https://www.w3.org/TR/2018/PR-exi-c14n-20180426/</loc>
</sitem>
<sitem>
            <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2016/CR-exi-c14n-20161103/"
                >https://www.w3.org/TR/2016/CR-exi-c14n-20161103/</loc>
</sitem>
<sitem>
            <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-exi-c14n-20150521/"
                >https://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-exi-c14n-20150521/</loc>
</sitem>
        </prevlocs>
        <latestloc>
            <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n/">https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n/</loc>
        </latestloc>
        <authlist>
            <author>
                <name>Sebastian K&#228;bisch</name>
                <affiliation>Siemens AG</affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Daniel Peintner</name>
                <affiliation>Siemens AG</affiliation>
            </author>
        </authlist>
        <abstract>
            <p>Any EXI document is part of a set of EXI documents that are logically equivalent
                within an application context, but which vary in physical representation based on
                differences permitted by the <bibref ref="exiSpec"/>. This specification describes a
                relatively simple method for generating a physical representation, the canonical
                form, of an EXI document that accounts for the permissible differences. An example
                of the applications targeted by this specification is one that needs to guarantee
                non-repudiation using XML Signature yet allows certain flexibility for
                intermediaries to reconstitute the documents before they reach final destination
                without breaking the signatures. Note that two documents may have differing
                canonical forms yet still be equivalent in a given context based on more elaborate
                application-specific equivalence rules which is out of scope of this specification.
            </p>
        </abstract>
        <status>
            <p>
                <emph>This section describes the status of this document at the time of its
                    publication. Other documents may supersede this document. A list of current W3C
                    publications and the latest revision of this technical report can be found in
                    the W3C technical reports index at <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/"
                        >https://www.w3.org/TR/</loc>.</emph>
            </p>

            <p>This is the W3C Recommendation of the Canonical EXI specification and it has
                been produced by the <loc href="https://www.w3.org/XML/EXI/">EXI Working
                Group</loc>. </p>


            <p>A <loc href="https://services.w3.org/htmldiff?doc1=https://www.w3.org/TR/2018/PR-exi-c14n-20180426/&amp;doc2=https://www.w3.org/TR/2018/REC-exi-c14n-20180531/">diff-marked </loc>version against the previous version of this document is available.  </p>

<p>Please send comments about this document as <loc href="https://github.com/w3c/exi-specs/issues">GitHub issues</loc> with label "Canonical EXI".</p>

           <p>The interoperability testing has been performed using test cases developed in the EXI <loc href="https://github.com/w3c/exi-testsuite">testsuite</loc>. An <loc href="https://www.w3.org/XML/EXI/implementation-report-c14n/">implementation report</loc> has been produced.</p>

            <p>This document was produced by a group operating under the <loc href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy/">W3C Patent Policy</loc>. W3C maintains a <loc rel="disclosure" href="https://www.w3.org/2004/01/pp-impl/38502/status">public list of any patent disclosures</loc> made in connection with the deliverables of the group; that page also includes instructions for disclosing a patent. An individual who has actual knowledge of a patent which the individual believes contains <loc href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy/#def-essential">Essential Claim(s)</loc> must disclose the information in accordance with <loc href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy/#sec-Disclosure">section 6 of the W3C Patent Policy</loc>.</p> 

<p>This document is governed by the <loc id="w3c_process_revision" href="https://www.w3.org/2018/Process-20180201/">1 February 2018 W3C Process Document</loc>. </p>


        </status>
        <langusage>
            <language id="en-US">English</language>
        </langusage>
        <revisiondesc>
            <p>Last Modified: $Date $</p>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <body>
        <div1 id="introduction">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The EXI 1.0 Recommendation <bibref ref="exiSpec"/> specifies the syntax of a class of
                resources called EXI streams. It is possible for EXI streams that are equivalent for
                the purposes of many applications to differ in physical representation. For example,
                they may differ in their datatype representation and attribute ordering. It is the
                goal of this specification to establish a method for determining whether two
                documents are equivalent, or whether an application has not changed a document,
                except for transformations permitted by EXI 1.0. </p>

            <div2 id="conventions">
                <head>Notational Conventions and Terminology</head>
                <p>The key words MUST, MUST NOT, REQUIRED, SHALL, SHALL NOT, SHOULD, SHOULD NOT,
                    RECOMMENDED, MAY, and OPTIONAL, when they appear EMPHASIZED in this document,
                    are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <bibref ref="RFC2119"/>.
                    <!--Other
                    terminology used to describe the EXI format is defined in the body of this
                    specification. --></p>
                <p>The term <term>canonical</term> is used throughout this document to denote a
                    normative form in regard to the physical representation. The term
                        <term>canonical EXI</term> refers to EXI that is in canonical form produced
                    by the method described in this specification. </p>

                <p>The term <term>sorted lexicographically</term> denotes lexicographical ordering
                    of strings which is done by comparing character by character. Individual
                    characters are ordered by comparing their Unicode code points. </p>

            </div2>

            <div2 id="motivation">
                <head>Motivation</head>
                <p>Many environments and device classes have difficulties handling plain-text XML
                    due to various reasons (e.g., document size and processing overhead). W3C's
                    Efficient XML Interchange (EXI) Format has been developed to provide a solution
                    to these issues and to extend the use of XML and its tools. </p>

                <p> With EXI, constrained environments and device classes (low memory, bandwidth,
                    and processing power) have the possibility to be part of the XML world. However,
                    some use cases also require a canonical representation of the XML-based data for
                    comparison of logical and physical equivalence. Hence, supporting EXI
                    canonicalization without going through plain-text XML where nothing else but EXI
                    is available is needed. </p>

                <p>In addition, EXI canonicalization is useful for traditional XML users. For
                    example, EXI canonicalization provides a type-aware canonicalization scheme that
                    can discern that +1, 1, 1.0, 1e0 and 1E0 are equivalent representations of the
                    same floating-point value. This allows intermediaries to use binding-models
                    and/or type-aware processing without breaking signatures. Moreover, with a fast
                    EXI processor, EXI canonicalization can be much faster than traditional XML
                    canonicalization and can help address some of the well-known processing
                    bottlenecks for XML security.</p>
            </div2>


            <div2>
                <head>Applications</head>
                <p> One application field for the canonical form of an XML-based document or
                    document subset is digital signature. During signature generation, the digest is
                    computed over the canonical form of the document or the document subset
                    respectively. The document is then transferred to the receiving party, which
                    validates the signature by reading the document and computing a digest of the
                    canonical form of the received document (see <specref
                        ref="signatureProcessingSteps"/>). If there is equivalence, the receiving
                    parties can ensure that the information content of the document has not been
                    altered since it was signed. </p>
                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>We still need to decide *what* gets hashed. The working group tends to
                        recommend that the hash is generated for the Canonical EXI stream taking
                        also into account EXI options (i.e. the EXI Header).</edtext>
                </ednote>-->

                <p>Although EXI supports plain-text XML Signature by preserving XML information such
                    as comments and prefixes (see <titleref
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-best-practices/#signature">EXI Best Practices
                        for XML Signature</titleref>) this optional strategy is not the most
                    efficient and is not well suited for all environments and use cases.
                    <!--Hence, supporting XML/EXI canonicalization and
                    signature without going through plain-text XML where nothing else but EXI is
                    available is needed. --></p>
                <!--<p> For example, it has been found to be important, that EXI provides a better way
                    to integrate with XML/EXI Signature. Currently EXI processors with appropriate
                    fidelity options can retain information needed by XML canonicalization. However,
                    it is desirable to better integrate with EXI and provide an EXI canonicalization
                    mechanism itself (see <titleref
                        href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-impacts/#xml-signature">EXI Impacts on XML
                        Signature</titleref>). </p>-->



                <!--<p>A digital EXI Signature is one prominent use case for Canonical EXI. A signed
                    document can be transmitted using EXI. As with XML, the receiver will need to
                    serialize the signed content using the selected EXI canonicalization algorithm
                    (e.g., <code>http://www.w3.org/TR/canonical-exi/</code>) to verify the
                    signature. The use of plain-text XML can be avoided completely.</p>-->
                <!--<p>
                    <ednote>
                        <edtext>How do we we differ whether EXI Signature demands an canonicalized
                            EXI document or fragment. Who needs to define whether an document is
                            encoded as EXI document or fragment? Do we need to provide two
                            signature-methods?</edtext>
                    </ednote>
                </p>-->

                <!--</div2>-->
                <!-- <div2> <head>Canonical EXI</head> <p>Canonical EXI is a form of EXI, 
				intended to allow relatively simple comparison of EXI streams for equivalence.</p> 
				<p>Signing EXI streams is to be done using the canonical EXI form.</p> </div2> -->

                <!--<div2>
                <head>Limitations</head>-->
                <p>It is the goal of this specification to provide a canonical EXI form for various
                    use-cases. For example, restricted and very limited devices should be able to
                    create or check against a canonical EXI stream. This applies to devices that may
                    be able to speak only a given EXI language (according to an XML Schema) or
                    support only a subset of all EXI features. </p>
                <!--<p>For example an EXI stream may or may not contain the EXI options that were used
                    to encode the stream. However, the process for building a Canonical EXI stream
                    is based on the knowledge of the used EXI options and MUST follow the rules
                    defined in <specref ref="canonicalEXI"/>. Moreover, there is not <emph>one</emph>
                    canonical EXI stream but potentially many
                    variants, according to the schema knowledge in use as well as the corresponding
                    EXI options and fidelity settings.
                </p>-->
            </div2>
        </div1>

        <div1 id="canonicalEXI">
            <head>Canonical EXI Stream</head>
            <p>The EXI specification defines an EXI stream as an EXI header followed by an EXI body.
                In this sense a Canonical EXI stream is a <specref ref="canonicalHeader"/> followed
                by a <specref ref="canonicalBody"/>.
                <!--Please note, for the sake of clarity and
                comprehensibility the order of the sections follow in reverse order.--></p>

            <p>EXI Canonicalization may be used as a canonicalization method algorithm in XML
                Signature <bibref ref="xmlSignature"/> and XML Encryption <bibref
                    ref="xmlEncryption"/>. This document specifies the following identifier <!-- <code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n</code>.-->
                <!--The identifier <code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n</code>
                hereby specifies the rules of this document.--></p>
            <p><code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n</code></p>

            <!--<table border="1" cellpadding="5">
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Canonical EXI Identifier</th>
                        <th>Effect</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td><code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n</code></td>
                        <td><emph>default</emph> (with EXI Options document)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr id="WithoutEXIOptions">
                        <td><code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n#WithoutEXIOptions</code></td>
                        <td>Without EXI Options document</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>-->

            <div2 id="canonicalOptions">
                <head>Canonical EXI Options</head>
                <p>The <term>Canonical EXI Options</term> provide a single, simple, unambiguous way
                    to express the EXI-C14N options. The following table describes the options that
                    may be specified in the Canonical EXI Options document.</p>

                <table class="tableBorders" id="CanonicalEXIOptions">
                    <caption>Canonical EXI Options in Canonical Options Document</caption>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Canonical EXI Option</th>
                            <th>Description</th>
                            <th>Default Value</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><termref def="omitOptionsDocument">omitOptionsDocument</termref>
                            </td>
                            <td>Omit EXI Options document</td>
                            <td>false</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><termref def="utcTime">utcTime</termref>
                            </td>
                            <td>Use Coordinated Universal Time (UTC)</td>
                            <td>false</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>

                <p>Appendix <specref ref="canonicalOptionsSchema"/> provides an XML Schema
                    describing the <term>Canonical EXI Options document</term>. This schema is
                    designed for efficient transmission by utilizing
                    <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#options">EXI options</loc>.</p>

                <p>
                    <termdef id="omitOptionsDocument" term="omitOptionsDocument"> The
                            <term>omitOptionsDocument option</term> specifies whether the <titleref
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-optionsDoc">EXI Options
                            document</titleref> is omitted. </termdef>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <termdef id="utcTime" term="utcTime"> The <term>utcTime option</term> is used to
                        specify whether Date-Time values must be represented using Coordinated
                        Universal Time (UTC, sometimes called "Greenwich Mean Time"). </termdef>
                </p>
            </div2>

        </div1>


        <div1 id="canonicalHeader">
            <head>Canonical EXI Header</head>
            <p>Each EXI stream begins with an EXI header. The EXI header identifies the version of
                the EXI format being used and specifies the options used to process the body of the
                EXI stream. The EXI header has the following structure: </p>

            <table class="tableBorders">
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td style="text-align: center;">[ EXI Cookie ]</td>
                        <td style="text-align: center;"> Distinguishing Bits </td>
                        <td style="text-align: center;">
                            <table class="tableNoBorders">
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td style="text-align: center; ">Presence Bit</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td style="text-align: center;">for EXI Options</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </td>
                        <td style="text-align: center;">
                            <table class="tableNoBorders">
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td style="text-align: center;">EXI Format</td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td style="text-align: center;">Version</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </td>
                        <td style="text-align: center;">[EXI Options]</td>
                        <td style="text-align: center;">[Padding Bits]</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>

            <p>A Canonical EXI Header MUST NOT begin with the optional EXI Cookie, and padding bits
                (if any) MUST always be represented as a sequence of 0 (zero) bits. </p>
            <p>If the Canonical EXI Option <termref def="omitOptionsDocument"
                    >omitOptionsDocument</termref> is equal to <code>true</code> the Presence Bit
                for EXI Options MUST be 0 (false) to indicate that the fifth part of the EXI Header,
                the EXI Options, is absent. If the Canonical EXI Option <termref
                    def="omitOptionsDocument">omitOptionsDocument</termref> is equal to
                    <code>false</code>, the Presence Bit for the EXI Options MUST be 1 (true) to
                indicate the EXI Options are present.
                <!--  On the contrary, if the Canonical EXI Identifier is not
                equal to <code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n#WithoutEXIOptions</code> the Presence
                Bit for EXI Options MUST be 1 (true) to indicate that the EXI Options are present. -->
            </p>

            <p>The <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#options">EXI Options</loc> are represented
                as an EXI Options
                document<!--,
                    which is an XML document encoded using the EXI format using
                    the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#optionsSchema">XML Schema for EXI Options Document</loc>-->.
                That said, the subsequently described canonicalization steps expect as input a set
                of EXI Options (or respectively an EXI options document) and produce as output a
                canonicalized set of EXI options that MUST be represented as <specref
                    ref="canonicalBody"/>. </p>

            <p>A canonical EXI Options document MUST respect the following constraints.</p>

            <olist>

                <item>
                    <p>An EXI Options element <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption">blockSize</loc> that
                        matches the default value (i.e., &lt;blockSize&gt;1000000&lt;/blockSize&gt;)
                        MUST be omitted.
                        <!--The EXI Options elements (i.e. <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-bytealignment">byte</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-precompression">pre-compress</loc>,
                            <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-selfContained"
                            >selfContained</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-valueMaxLengthOption"
                            >valueMaxLength</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-valuePartitionCapacityOption"
                            >valuePartitionCapacity</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption">dtd</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption">prefixes</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption">lexicalValues</loc>,
                            <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption">comments</loc>,
                            <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption">pis</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption">blockSize</loc>,
                            <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-compressionOption"
                            >compression</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-fragmentOption">fragment</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-schemaIdOption">schemaId</loc>, <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-strictOption">strict</loc>) that
                        match the default value (e.g., &lt;blockSize&gt;1000000&lt;/blockSize&gt;)
                        MUST be omitted (see <loc
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#exiOptionsInOptionsField">EXI
                            specification</loc> for default values).--></p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>The element <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption"
                            >blockSize</loc> MUST be omitted if neither compression nor pre-compress
                        is present.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>When the alignment option <loc
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-compressionOption">compression</loc>
                        is set, <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-precompression"
                            >pre-compress</loc> MUST be used instead of <loc
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-compressionOption"
                        >compression</loc>.</p>
                </item>
                <!--<item>
                    <p>The element <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-schemaIdOption"
                            >schemaId</loc> MAY be used to identify the schema information used for
                        processing the EXI body.
                    </p>
                </item>-->
                <item>
                    <p>When the value of the Preserve.lexicalValues fidelity option is true the
                        element <loc
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-datatypeRepresentationOption"
                            >datatypeRepresentationMap</loc> MUST be omitted. When the value of the
                        Preserve.lexicalValues fidelity option is false and the element <loc
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-datatypeRepresentationOption"
                            >datatypeRepresentationMap</loc> does have nested element tuples (tuple
                        of schema datatype and datatype representation), the tuples are to be sorted
                        lexicographically according to the schema datatype first by {name} then by
                        {namespace}. Moreover, the <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#eventTypes"
                            >EXI event</loc> sequence of each nested element MUST be Start Element
                        (SE) followed by End Element (EE). Mappings that match the default built-in
                        EXI datatype representations map (e.g.,
                        {http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema}base64Binary &#8594;
                        {http://www.w3.org/2009/exi}base64Binary) MUST be omitted.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>The <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-userMetaData">user defined
                            meta-data</loc> MUST NOT be used unless it conveys a convention used by
                        the application. At the time of writing the only available convention is the
                            <bibref ref="exiProfile"/>. The associated exi:p element MUST always be
                        represented using the following sequence of EXI events: A SE(exi:p) event,
                        followed by an AT(xsi:type)="xsd:decimal" event, followed by a CH event,
                        followed by an EE event. </p>
                    <note>
                        <p> The user defined meta-data conveys auxiliary information and does not
                            alter or extend the EXI data format. Hence it is deemed acceptable to
                            omit this information.</p>
                    </note>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Elements that are necessary to structure the EXI options document according
                        to the XML schema (i.e. lesscommon, uncommon, alignment,
                        datatypeRepresentationMap, preserve and common) MUST be omitted
                            <emph>unless</emph> there is at least one nested element according to
                        the previous steps.</p>
                </item>
            </olist>

            <p>The example below illustrates some requirements and the associated modifications that
                have been described.</p>

            <example>
                <head>EXI Options vs. Canonical EXI Options</head>
                <table style="border: 0px;">
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td style="vertical-align: text-top;"
                                ><eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;exi:header 
    xmlns:exi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2009/exi&quot;&gt;
    &lt;exi:lesscommon&gt;
        &lt;exi:preserve/&gt;
        &lt;exi:blockSize&gt;1000000&lt;/exi:blockSize&gt;
    &lt;/exi:lesscommon&gt;
    &lt;exi:common&gt;
        &lt;exi:compression/&gt;
        &lt;exi:fragment/&gt;
    &lt;/exi:common&gt;
&lt;/exi:header&gt;</eg></td>
                            <td> &#8594; </td>
                            <td style="vertical-align: text-top;"
                                ><eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;exi:header 
   xmlns:exi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2009/exi&quot;&gt;
   &lt;exi:lesscommon&gt;
       &lt;exi:uncommon&gt;
           &lt;exi:alignment&gt;
               &lt;exi:pre-compress/&gt;
           &lt;/exi:alignment&gt; 
       &lt;/exi:uncommon&gt; 
   &lt;/exi:lesscommon&gt;   
   &lt;exi:common&gt;
        &lt;exi:fragment/&gt;
   &lt;/exi:common&gt;
&lt;/exi:header&gt;
                            
                            
                            </eg></td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </example>



            <!-- space -->
            <p>&#160;</p>
            <warning>
                <p> Applications that use Canonical EXI need to ensure that the senders and
                    the receivers of EXI documents are using the same schema information.
                    This is regardless schemaId is included in the header options or not.
                    Failure to do so may result in producing an uncomparable (and perhaps
                    undecipherable) EXI document.</p>
            </warning>
            
            

            <!--            <ednote>
                <edtext>[DP] We still need to define the actual "content" of the EXI options
                document (default options vs. non-default options, empty elements with a
                pre-defined EXI event sequence, schemaId, ...).</edtext>
                </ednote>-->


        </div1>

        <div1 id="canonicalBody">
            <head>Canonical EXI Body</head>
            <p>The subsequently described EXI Canonicalization steps and algorithms expect as input
                XML information items. Each information item is mapped to its respective set of EXI
                events (see <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#eventTypes">Table 4-1 in EXI
                    specification</titleref>) and produces as output a canonicalized EXI body
                stream.
                <!--Hence, the sequence of <titleref
                    href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#eventTypes">EXI events</titleref> (e.g., SE, NS,
                and AT events) produces as output a
                canonicalized EXI body stream.-->
                Following the presented algorithms guarantees that logically-identical documents
                produce identical serialized EXI body stream representations (assuming the same EXI
                coding options). </p>
            <p> Each event in an EXI stream participates in a mapping system that relates events to
                XML Information Items so that an EXI document or an EXI fragment as a whole serves
                to represent an <bibref ref="XMLInfoset"/>. Appendix B Infoset Mapping of <bibref
                    ref="exiSpec"/> describes the mapping system in detail. </p>
            <note>
                <p>An EXI stream can be passed to a final recipient over multiple intermediate
                    nodes. In general, it is feasible to parse and re-encode the EXI stream on such
                    an intermediate node without affecting the canonical EXI stream. However, please
                    note that alternating <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#options">EXI
                        Options</titleref> (e.g., <titleref
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveOption">preserve
                        option</titleref> or <titleref
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-schemaIdOption">schemaId</titleref>)
                    used to encode the body of the EXI stream, may lead to irrecoverable data loss
                    or differences. The same issue applies to XML intermediate nodes (e.g.,
                    intermediate nodes removing DTDs et cetera). </p>
            </note>
            <div2 id="exiAlignment">
                <head>EXI Alignment Options and Streams</head>
                <p>EXI provides four alignment options, namely <emph>bit-packed</emph>,
                        <emph>byte-alignment</emph>, <emph>pre-compression</emph>, and
                        <emph>compression</emph>. </p>
                <p> The canonicalized EXI form is the resulting EXI stream following the rules
                    defined in this document. When the alignment option <emph>compression</emph> is
                    set for an EXI stream, its canonical form is computed as if the EXI stream was
                    encoded using the alignment option <emph>pre-compression</emph> instead.</p>

                <p>EXI processors may make use of padding bits, for example to make the length of
                    the EXI stream byte-aligned. If used, the padding bits in a Canonical EXI stream
                    MUST always be represented as a sequence of 0 (zero) bits. </p>
                <!--<p>Each EXI stream begins with an <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#header"
                        >EXI Header</titleref> but it MUST NOT be taken into account when building
                    the canonical EXI form. </p>-->
                <!--<p>
                    <ednote>
                        <edtext>Decide whether EXI options need to be present in any case and IF so
                            what about default options such as bit-packed.</edtext>
                    </ednote>
                </p>-->
            </div2>

            <div2 id="exiEvents">
                <head>EXI Event Selection</head>
                <p> EXI processors represent a given event such as a start element or an attribute
                    by serializing an <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-eventcode">event
                        code</titleref> first, followed by the corresponding event content. Each
                    event code is represented by a sequence of 1 to 3 parts that uniquely identifies
                    an event. </p>
                <p> In situations where EXI grammars provide more than one possible event the
                    canonical EXI form prescribes which event (and respectively which event code)
                    has to be chosen. That said, it is not uncommon that an EXI processor has
                    certain flexibility in choosing the appropriate EXI grammar production, or
                    respectively the appropriate event. </p>

                <p>Canonical EXI processors MUST follow a two <!--three--> step process for
                    selecting the one valid event(-code):</p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item><p><specref ref="exiConventions"/></p></item>
                        <item><p><specref ref="exiEventMatching"/></p></item>
                    </ulist>
                <div3 id="exiConventions">
                    <head>Select productions according to specific conventions</head>
                    <p>The availability of grammar productions is subject to the convention used by
                        the application. A prominent convention is the <bibref ref="exiProfile"/>,
                        which is more restrictive in regard to which production is usable than the
                            <bibref ref="exiSpec"/> specification. </p>
                    <note>
                        <p>The EXI Profile uses the xsi:type attribute to switch from an evolving
                            built-in element grammar to a non-evolving schema-informed grammar. The
                            specification mentions in particular the xsd:anyType complex type but
                            does not require this specific type. Canonical EXI processors MUST use
                            xsd:anyType.</p>
                    </note>
                </div3>
                <!--<div3>
                    <head>Select productions according to event content</head>
                    <p>In the case of an attribute (AT) or a character (CH) event, productions MUST
                        be selected that can be used to represent the content value most precisely
                        (e.g., the content value "123" can be represented with the schema-typed EXI
                        Integer datatype but also with the untyped EXI String representation).</p>


                    <p>For Character content the order is as follows: </p>
                    <olist spacing="compact">
                        <item>
                            <p>SE( qname ) CH [schema-typed value]</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>SE ( uri : * ) CH [schema-typed value]</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>SE ( * ) CH [schema-typed value]</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>SE (qname) CH [untyped value]</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>SE (*) CH [untyped value]</p>
                        </item>
                    </olist>
                    <ednote>
                        <edtext>Do we need the preceeding SE event or is it handled by the next
                            Section 4.2.3</edtext>
                    </ednote>

                    <p>For Attribute content the order is as follows: </p>
                    <olist>
                        <item>
                            <p>AT ( qname ) [schema-typed value]</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>AT ( uri : * ) [schema-typed value]</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>AT ( * ) [schema-typed value]</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>AT (qname) [untyped value]</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>AT (*) [untyped value]</p>
                        </item>
                    </olist>
                </div3>-->
                <div3 id="exiEventMatching">
                    <head>Use the event that matches most precisely</head>
                    <p>After excluding productions that are not usable (according to the convention
                        in use) a canonical EXI processor MUST use the event that matches the
                        following prioritized heuristics most precisely.</p>
                    <olist>
                        <item>
                            <!--<p>Use the event with the most accurate event content first</p>-->
                            <p>For Start Element (SE) events the order is as follows: </p>
                            <olist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>SE ( <emph>qname</emph> )</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>SE ( <emph>uri : *</emph> ) </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>SE ( <emph>*</emph> )</p>
                                </item>
                            </olist>
                            <p>For Character (CH) events the order is as follows: </p>
                            <olist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>CH [schema-typed value]</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>CH [untyped value]</p>
                                </item>
                            </olist>
                            <p>For Attribute (AT) events the order is as follows: </p>
                            <olist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>AT ( <emph>qname</emph> ) [schema-typed value]</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>AT ( <emph>qname</emph> ) [untyped value]</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>AT ( <emph>uri : *</emph> )</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>AT ( <emph>*</emph> )</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>AT ( <emph>*</emph> ) [untyped value]</p>
                                </item>
                            </olist>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>IF the representational accuracy is unaffected, then use the event
                                with the least number event code parts.</p>
                            <!--<p>An <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-eventcode">event
                                    code</titleref> is a sequence of 1 to 3 non-negative integers
                                called parts used to identify each event in an EXI stream. </p>-->
                        </item>
                        <!--<item>
                            <p>IF the number of event code parts is also equal, use the event with
                            the smaller event code</p>
                            </item>-->
                    </olist>

                    <!-- Next para removed. Not necessary anymore -->
                    <!--<p>Further, a value content item that can be represented by the associated EXI
                        datatype MUST be represented with the associated datatype representation.
                        When the <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-strictOption"
                            >strict</titleref> option is false, attributes and character events that
                        cannot be represented by the associated EXI datatype representations (e.g.,
                        schema-invalid values) MUST use the additional untyped AT and CH terminal
                        symbols. </p> -->
                    <note>
                        <p>The verification is solely based on EXI grammars and EXI
                            datatypes. A Canonical EXI processor does not account for XML schema validity
                            (similar to an EXI processor) in order to maintain high-performance
                            efficiency.</p>
                    </note>


                    <p>The appendix section <specref ref="exampleEventSelection"/> depicts one
                        concrete example for choosing the correct event.</p>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="exiContentHandling">
                <head>EXI Content Handling</head>

                <div3 id="excludeExtraneousEvents">
                    <head>Exclude extraneous events </head>
                    <p>The EXI grammars permit EXI processors to include extraneous empty-string
                        CH&#160;("") events that are not required by the grammar and do not change
                        the resulting XML Infoset of the produced document.</p>
                    
                    <p>Canonical EXI MUST exclude extraneous CH&#160;("") events unless they are
                        required by the EXI grammar.</p>
                    
                    <!--<p>When the current element grammar contains a production of the form
                        <emph>LeftHandSide</emph> : EE, EXI can represent the content of an
                        empty element explicitly as an empty CH event or implicitly as a SE event
                        immediately followed by an EE event. In these circumstances, Canonical EXI
                        MUST represent an empty element by a SE event followed by an EE event.</p>-->
                    
                    
                    
                    <note>
                        <p>EXI grammars may still require empty-string CH&#160;("") events. An example are elements typed as String (e.g.,
                            element <code>foo</code> typed as <code>xsd:string</code>).
                            When Strict is True an event sequence <emph>SE&#160;(foo) EE</emph> cannot be used.
                            Instead <emph>SE&#160;(foo) CH&#160;("") EE</emph> is required for the following strict simple type grammar. </p>
                        <example id="exampleSimpleTypeGrammar">
                            <head><emph>Strict</emph> Simple Type grammar</head>
                            <table>
                                <tbody>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td>Type <sub>i, 0</sub></td>
                                        <td>:</td>
                                        <td></td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td></td>
                                        <td></td>
                                        <td>CH[schema-typed value] Type <sub>i, 1</sub></td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td>Type <sub>i, 1</sub></td>
                                        <td>:</td>
                                        <td></td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td></td>
                                        <td></td>
                                        <td>EE</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </tbody>
                            </table>
                        </example>
                    </note>
                    
                    
                    <!--<note>
                        <p>@TODO check/update: The only time the EXI grammars require an extraneous
                        CH&#160;("") event is for encoding empty element content when strict is
                        true (see Approach A).</p>
                        </note>-->
                    <p>Moreover, applications due to various reasons may send a series of
                        consecutive CH events. Canonical EXI MUST merge consecutive CH events to a
                            <emph>single</emph> CH event.</p>
                    


                    
                    <!--<ednote>
                        <edtext>Does it make sense to combine the two sections <specref
                        ref="emptyElementContent"/> and <specref
                        ref="excludeExtraneousEvents"/>. </edtext>
                        </ednote>-->
                <!--</div3>-->


                <!--<div3 id="emptyElementContent">
                    <head>Empty element content</head>-->
                    <!--<ednote>
                        <edtext> There are two approaches proposed on how to define rules regarding
                            the encoding of empty elements in schema-informed context. Please
                            provide any opinions as to which of those approaches you consider more
                            appropriate to have as part of Canonical EXI. Note the approach B
                            provides better efficiency, while approach A leads to generate the same
                            sequence of events whether strict or non-strict mode.</edtext>
                    </ednote>-->
                    <!--<div4>
                        <head>Approach A</head>
                        <p>A canonical EXI processor MUST add a CH event with a String of length 0
                            (zero) </p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>if processing the EE event of an XML Information item fails by
                                    means of existing event codes of length 1 (i.e., no EE exists),
                                    and</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>when processing a schema-informed grammar where a CH
                                    [schema-typed value] event code of length 1 exists that allows
                                    for a String of length 0 (zero)</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>

                        <ednote>
                            <edtext>This approach always first tries to encode empty elements (i.e.
                                SE followed by EE, optionally AT, etc. in between) as a sequence of
                                SE CH EE (optionally AT etc. between SE and CH) where CH is used for
                                representing empty string, for elements defined to have
                                simple-content, as long as doing so is possible (i.e. unless the
                                codec in effect does *not* permit to encode empty string
                                "").</edtext>
                        </ednote>

                    </div4>-->
                    <!--<div4>
                        <head>Approach B</head>-->
                    <!--<p>When the current element grammar contains a production of the form
                            <emph>LeftHandSide</emph> : EE, EXI can represent the content of an
                        empty element explicitly as an empty CH event or implicitly as a SE event
                        immediately followed by an EE event. In these circumstances, Canonical EXI
                        MUST represent an empty element by a SE event followed by an EE event.</p>-->
                    <!--<ednote>
                            <edtext>This approach encodes empty elements (i.e. SE followed by EE,
                                optionally AT, etc. in between) as a sequence of SE EE (optionally
                                AT etc. in between). As an exception, for elements defined to have
                                simple-content, it is allowed to insert CH that represents empty
                                string "" between SE and EE only when doing so is necessary for
                                representing an empty element there. </edtext>
                        </ednote>-->
                    <!--</div4>-->

                    
                </div3>


                <div3 id="whitespaceHandling">
                    <head>Whitespace Handling</head>
                    <p>In general, Canonical EXI SHALL not change XML Information items. One
                        exception to this statement is significant whitespace characters. Except as
                        specified below, Canonical EXI MUST respect
                            <code>xml:space="preserve"</code>.
                        <!--Canonical
                        EXI SHOULD follow the subsequent whitespace handling rules.--></p>
                    <!--<p>First of all <code>xml:space="preserve"</code> MUST be respected when it is
                        in effect in the document (i.e., all
                        whitespace characters are preserved).</p>
                    <p/>-->

                    <note>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>It is not possible to respect whitespace-handling rules in all
                                    situations. For example when the grammar in effect is a
                                    schema-informed grammar and xml:space is "preserve". For
                                    example, the value " 123 " (with a leading and trailing space
                                    character) typed as xsd:int cannot preserve the heading and
                                    trailing whitespace when typed datatype representation is
                                    used.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Use-cases requiring whitespace preservation might consider using
                                    the <titleref
                                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveLexicalValuesOption"
                                        > Preserve.lexicalValues</titleref> option set to true. When
                                    Preserve.lexicalValues is true CH [schema-typed value] and AT
                                    [schema-typed value] productions MUST be used in all cases given
                                    that the restricted character sets can represent any string
                                    value. </p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </note>

                    <p>When the current <code>xml:space</code> is not <code>"preserve"</code>,
                        different rules apply for <specref ref="whitespaceSimpleData"/> and <specref
                            ref="whitespaceComplexData"/>.</p>


                    <div4 id="whitespaceSimpleData">
                        <head>Simple Whitespace Data</head>
                        <p>The term <emph>simple data</emph> refers to data between SE and EE (i.e.,
                            Start&#160;Element tag followed by End&#160;Element tag).</p>
                        <p>When the grammar in effect is a schema-informed grammar
                            <!--apply lexical
                            rule and -->use <xspecref
                                href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/#dt-whiteSpace"
                                >whiteSpace facet</xspecref> if any to normalize whitespaces.</p>
                        <p>When the grammar in effect is a schema-less grammar, then all whitespaces
                            MUST be preserved.</p>
                    </div4>

                    <div4 id="whitespaceComplexData">
                        <head>Complex Whitespace Data</head>
                        <p>The term <emph>complex data</emph> refers to data between SE and SE, EE
                            and SE, or EE and EE.</p>
                        <p>For complex data, whitespaces nodes (i.e., strings that consist solely of
                            whitespaces) MUST be removed.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>


            </div2>

            <div2 id="exiStreamOrder">
                <head>Stream Order</head>
                <p>In general, a canonical EXI processor SHALL NOT change the order of the input
                    sequence. The only exceptions to this statement are sequences of attributes
                    and/or namespace declarations. </p>

                <p>The EXI specification defines that namespace (NS) and attribute (AT) events
                    associated with a given element occur directly after the start element (SE)
                    event in the following order:</p>

                <table class="tableBorders" style="padding: 10px;">
                    <!-- border="0" rules="cols"-->
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <!--<td style="text-align: center;" >SC</td>-->
                            <td style="text-align: center;">NS</td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;">NS</td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;">...</td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;">NS</td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;"> AT (xsi:type) </td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;"> AT (xsi:nil) </td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;">AT</td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;">AT</td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;">...</td>
                            <td style="text-align: center;">AT</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>

                <p>In addition, canonical EXI specifies that namespace declarations for a given
                    element MUST be sorted lexicographically according to the NS prefix. Further,
                    canonical EXI strictly requires that an xsi:type or an xsi:nil attribute MUST
                    occur before other AT events even if it does not impact grammar selection.
                    Moreover, attributes other than xsi:type and xsi:nil for a given element MUST be
                    sorted lexicographically, first by qname local-name then by qname uri. </p>
                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>How do we deal with namespace declarations? Superfluous namespace
                        declarations are to be removed from each element do avoid issues...</edtext>
                </ednote>-->

                <p/>

                <!--                <note>
                    <p>When it is stated that strings (e.g., NS prefix and qname uri) are sorted in
                        lexicographical order, it is done so character by character, and the order
                        among characters is determined by comparing their Unicode code points. </p>
                </note>-->

                <note>
                    <p>Optimizations such as pruning <emph>insignificant</emph> xsi:type values
                        (e.g., <code>xsi:type="xsd:string"</code> for string values) or
                            <emph>insignificant</emph> xsi:nil values (e.g.,
                            <code>xsi:nil="false"</code>) are prohibited for a Canonical EXI
                        processor.</p>
                    <p>For example, EXI Profile uses the xsi:type attribute (e.g.,
                            <code>xsi:type="xsd:anyType"</code>) to switch to a non-evolving
                        schema-informed grammar. </p>
                </note>
                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>How do we guarantee that an EXI processor does not prune insignificant
                        xsi:type values (e.g., xsi:type="xsd:string" for string values) or
                        insignificant xsi:nil values (e.g., xsi:nil="false"). Should we mention that
                        this kind of "optimization" is not allowed for a canonical EXI
                        processor?</edtext>
                </ednote>-->
            </div2>


            <div2 id="datatypes">
                <head>EXI Datatypes</head>
                <p> This section describes the built-in EXI datatype representations used for
                    representing content items in canonical EXI streams. </p>


                <p> When the <titleref
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveLexicalValuesOption">
                        Preserve.lexicalValues</titleref> option is true, individual items are
                    represented as String. Each value MUST be represented as a String with the
                    associated restricted character set, if such a set is defined for the associated
                    datatype representation (see <titleref
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#builtInRestrictedStrings"> Restricted
                        Character Sets for Built-in EXI Datatype Representations</titleref>). String
                    content items associated with a restricted character MUST also follow the rules
                    described in <specref ref="dt-RCS"/>. </p>
                <p> When the <titleref
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-preserveLexicalValuesOption">
                        Preserve.lexicalValues</titleref> option is false, a value content item MUST
                    be represented with the associated datatype representation. The following
                    sub-sections describe the Canonical EXI behavior for datatypes that otherwise
                    may not lead to a uniquely defined representation. </p>


                <!--<p>EXI 1.0 permits the use of untyped AT or CH terminal symbols to represent a value
                    content item even when a typed AT or CH terminal symbol is available that could
                    have been used to represent the value. Therefore, given an input value content
                    item that uses an untyped AT or CH terminal symbol despite the availability of a
                    typed alternative terminal symbol, it is not apparent whether the use of the
                    untyped terminal symbol was due to the result of observing the event selection
                    rule described in Section <specref ref="exiEventSelection"/> or otherwise (i.e.
                    negligence of observing the rule) unless switching to the typed alternative
                    terminal symbol is actually attempted by a Canonical EXI processor. To cope with
                    this situation, Canonical EXI processors SHOULD be able to convert an untyped
                    value into each of the datatype representations defined in EXI 1.0 as long as
                    the target datatype representation can accept the value. </p>-->


                <div3 id="dt-unsignedInteger">
                    <head>Unsigned Integer</head>
                    <p>The EXI specification defines that the <titleref
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#encodingUnsignedInteger">Unsigned
                            Integer</titleref> datatype representation supports unsigned integer
                        numbers of arbitrary magnitude. EXI processors SHOULD support arbitrarily
                        large Unsigned Integer values. EXI processors MUST support Unsigned Integer
                        values less than 2147483648.</p>
                    <p>Canonical EXI processors MUST use the Unsigned Integer datatype
                        representation even if a value goes beyond the value 2147483647.</p>
                </div3>


                <div3 id="dt-enumeration">
                    <head>Enumeration</head>
                    <p> The <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#encodingEnumerations">EXI
                            Enumeration</titleref> assigns to each item an unsigned integer value
                        that corresponds to its ordinal position in the enumeration in schema-order
                        starting with position zero. When there is more than one item that
                        represents the same value in the enumeration, the value MUST be represented
                        by using the first ordinal position that represents the value. </p>
                </div3>

                <div3 id="dt-decimal">
                    <head>Decimal</head>
                    <p> The <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#encodingDecimal">EXI
                            Decimal</titleref> datatype is a Boolean sign followed by two Unsigned
                        Integers. A sign value of zero (0) is used to represent positive Decimal
                        values and a sign value of one (1) is used to represent negative Decimal
                        values. The first Unsigned Integer represents the integral portion of the
                        Decimal value. The second Unsigned Integer represents the fractional portion
                        of the Decimal value with the digits in reverse order to preserve leading
                        zeros. </p>
                    <p>The canonical EXI Decimal MUST respect the following constraint. </p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>The sign value MUST be zero (0) if both
                                <!--A sign value of one (1) MUST be changed to zero (0) if both-->
                                the integral portion and the fractional portion of the Decimal value
                                are 0 (zero).</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>
                </div3>

                <div3 id="dt-float">
                    <head>Float</head>
                    <p> The <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#encodingFloat">EXI
                            Float</titleref> datatype uses two consecutive EXI Integers.
                        <!--(see
						<titleref href="#integer">EXI
						Integer</titleref> )-->
                        The first Integer represents the mantissa of the floating point number and
                        the second Integer represents the base-10 exponent of the floating point
                        number. </p>
                    <p>The canonical EXI Float MUST respect the following constraints. </p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>A mantissa value of -0 is not permitted.
                                <!--MUST be changed to 0.--></p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>An exponent value of -0 is not permitted.
                                <!--MUST be changed to 0.-->
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>If the mantissa is 0 and the exponent value is not -(2<sup>14</sup>)
                                the exponent MUST be 0.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>If the mantissa is not 0, mantissas MUST have no trailing zeros.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>If the exponent value is -(2<sup>14</sup>) and the mantissa value is
                                neither 1 nor -1, to indicate the special value not-a-number (NaN),
                                the mantissa MUST be 0.</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>
                    <p>Given an EXI Float value that consists of one integer representing its
                        mantissa and the other integer representing its exponent, Canonical EXI
                        processors MUST find an equivalent canonical EXI Float that satisfies the
                        above constraints, where the rules of determining equivalence are described
                        below. </p>
                    <p>Two floats A and B each denoted as (mantissa, exponent) pair of (mA, eA) and
                        (mB, eB) where eA >= eB are equivalent under the following circumstances. </p>
                    <olist>
                        <item>
                            <p>Both mantissa and exponent are the same between the two floats. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p> Otherwise, if two exponents are different (i.e. eA > eB), substitute
                                A with A2 where A2 has exponent eB and mantissa mA *
                                    10<sup>(eA-eB)</sup>. If A2 and B are equivalent values per the
                                rule 1 above, A and B are equivalent. </p>
                        </item>
                    </olist>
                    <p>The appendix section <specref ref="exampleFloat"/> depicts one example
                        algorithm for finding the canonical EXI Float that is equivalent to a given
                        EXI Float value.</p>
                </div3>


                <div3 id="dt-dateTime">
                    <head>Date-Time</head>
                    <p> The <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#encodingDateTime">EXI
                            Date-Time</titleref> is a sequence of values representing the individual
                        components of the Date-Time. </p>
                    <p>The canonical EXI Date-Time MUST respect the following constraints. </p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>The Hour value used to compute the Time component MUST NOT be 24.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>The optional FractionalSecs component MUST be omitted if its value is
                                zero. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>If the Canonical EXI Option <termref def="utcTime">utcTime</termref>
                                is equal to <code>true</code>, Date-Time values must be represented
                                using Coordinated Universal Time (UTC, sometimes called "Greenwich
                                Mean Time"). Doing so requires applying the algorithm defined in
                                <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#adding-durations-to-dateTimes">
                                    adding durations to dateTimes</titleref> <bibref ref="schemaDatatypes2"/>
                                <emph>without</emph> modifying the value of seconds.</p>
                            <!--<ednote>
                                <edtext>Do we need further information such as canonical dateTime
                                    representation: <xspecref
                                        href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/#dateTime-canonical-representation"
                                        >XML Schema dateTime canonical representation</xspecref>) or
                                    a statement that the component TimeZone MUST be zero and/or
                                    whether the optional component TimeZone MUST be omitted or
                                    zero.</edtext>
                            </ednote>-->
                        </item>
                    </ulist>


                    <!--<p>If the component TimeZone is available the Date-Time values MUST be
                        normalized according to UTC by using the <xspecref
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/#adding-durations-to-dateTimes"
                            >addition operation defined in XML Schema Datatypes</xspecref>. </p>-->
                    <!--<p>The components of the Date-Time MUST NOT be canonicalized (e.g., according to
                            <xspecref
                            href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/#dateTime-canonical-representation"
                            >XML Schema dateTime canonical representation</xspecref>).</p>-->
                </div3>

                <!-- . A Float value 1.0 can be represented as 1 (mantissa) and 0 (exponent) 
					but also as 10E-1 et cetera </p> <p>The EXI Canonicalization requires the 
					two integeres to look as follows: <olist> <item> <p>Option: ...</p> </item> 
					<item> <p>Option: ...</p> </item> </olist> </p> -->


                <div3 id="dt-string">
                    <head>String and String Table</head>
                    <p>The EXI String datatype representation is a length-prefixed sequence of
                        characters. If no restricted character set is defined for the string, each
                        character is represented by its Unicode code point. The Unicode standard
                        allows multiple different representations of certain characters. A canonical
                        EXI processor MUST NOT change the code points (see appendix <specref
                            ref="decisionUnicode"/> for the rationale). </p>


                    <p>In EXI a string value content item is assigned to two partitions, a "local"
                        value partition and the global value partition (see <loc
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#encodingOptimizedForMisses">Partitions
                            Optimized for Frequent use of String Literals</loc>). When a string
                        value is found in the global or "local" partition, it may be represented
                        using a compact identifier. In Canonical EXI a string value MUST be
                        represented using a compact identifier if possible. Unless a convention was
                        indicated in <specref ref="canonicalOptions"/> by an application to dictate
                        differently (e.g., EXI Profile parameter localValuePartitions set to "0"),
                        EXI processors MUST first try to use the "local" compact identifier, and
                        only when this is not successful then try to use the global compact
                        identifier. </p>
                    <note>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>One of the reasons the attempt to represent the string value as a
                                    "local" compact identifier may fail is because the string has
                                    already been used as a "local" compact identifier previously.
                                    EXI supports only one local partitions entry per value.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>When a string value is not found in the global or "local" value
                                    partition a processor MAY also need to follow the rules
                                    described in <specref ref="dt-RCS"/> according to the given
                                    restricted character set, if available.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </note>
                    <p>Note that a Canonical EXI processor MUST also respect the XML schema
                            <xspecref
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/#dt-whiteSpace"
                            >whiteSpace facet</xspecref>, if defined.</p>
                    <!--<ednote>
                        <edtext>The W3C is standardizing on Unicode Normalization Form and
                            recommending all web data be stored and transmitted in this form. It may
                            be useful to state this and reference the relevant W3C specification
                            here: http://www.w3.org/TR/charmod-norm/</edtext>
                    </ednote>-->

                </div3>


                <div3 id="dt-RCS">
                    <head>Restricted Character Sets</head>
                    <p>
                        <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#restrictedCharSet">Restricted
                            Character Sets</titleref> are applied in EXI to restrict the characters
                        of the string datatype. The canonical representation dictates that
                        characters from the restricted character set MUST use the according <loc
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#encodingBoundedUnsigned"
                                    ><phrase><emph>n</emph></phrase>-bit Unsigned Integer</loc>.
                        Hence, only characters that are not in the set SHALL be represented by the
                            <emph>n</emph>-bit Unsigned Integer N followed by the Unicode code point
                        for each character represented as an Unsigned Integer.</p>
                </div3>

                <div3 id="dt-reprMap">
                    <head>Datatype Representation Map</head>
                    <p>The EXI option <titleref
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#datatypeRepresentationMap"
                            >datatypeRepresentationMap</titleref> may specify an alternate set of
                        datatype representations for typed values in the EXI body stream. This
                        specification does not define any canonicalization rules for alternate
                        representations. Other specifications and/or groups making use of this
                        feature MAY describe a canonical form.</p>
                </div3>

            </div2>

        </div1>

    </body>






    <back>

        <div1 id="references">
            <head>References</head>
            <blist>
                <!--<bibl id="exiSpec" key="Efficient XML Interchange (EXI) Format 1.0"
                    href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2011/REC-exi-20110310/">
                    <titleref>Efficient XML Interchange (EXI) Format 1.0</titleref> , John Schneider
                    and Takuki Kamiya, Editors. World Wide Web Consortium. The latest version is
                    available at <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/">
                    http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/</loc> . </bibl>-->
                <bibl id="exiSpec" key="EXI Format 1.0"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2014/REC-exi-20140211/">
                    <titleref>Efficient XML Interchange (EXI) Format 1.0 (Second
                    Edition)</titleref>, John Schneider, Takuki Kamiya, Daniel Peintner, Rumen
                    Kyusakov, Editors. World Wide Web Consortium. The latest version is available at
                        <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/"> https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/</loc>. </bibl>
                <!--<bibl id="exiEval" key="EXI Evaluation Note"
                    href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2009/WD-exi-evaluation-20090407/">
                    <titleref>Efficient XML Interchange Evaluation</titleref> , Carine Bournez,
                    Editor. World Wide Web Consortium. The latest version is available at <loc
                    href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-evaluation/">
                    http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-evaluation/</loc> . </bibl>-->
                <bibl id="schemaDatatypes2" key="XML Schema Datatypes"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/">
                    <titleref>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second Edition</titleref> , P. Byron and
                    A. Malhotra, Editors. World Wide Web Consortium, 2 May 2001, revised 28 October
                    2004. The latest version is available at <loc
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/">
                        https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2</loc> . </bibl>
                <bibl id="xmlCanonicalSpec" key="Canonical XML"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-c14n11-20080502/">
                    <titleref>Canonical XML Version 1.1</titleref> John Boyer and Glenn Marcy,
                    Editors. World Wide Web Consortium, W3C Recommendation 2 May 2008. The latest
                    version is available at <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-c14n11/">
                        https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-c14n11/</loc> . </bibl>
                <bibl id="XMLInfoset" key="XML Information Set"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xml-infoset-20040204/">
                    <titleref>XML Information Set (Second Edition)</titleref>, J. Cowan and R.
                    Tobin, Editors. World Wide Web Consortium, 24 October 2001, revised 4 February
                    2004. This version is https://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xml-infoset-20040204. The
                    latest version is available at <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-infoset/">
                        https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-infoset</loc>. </bibl>
                <bibl id="exiImpacts" key="EXI Impacts"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2008/WD-exi-impacts-20080903/">
                    <titleref>Efficient XML Interchange (EXI) Impacts</titleref> , Jaakko
                    Kangasharju, Editor. World Wide Web Consortium. The latest version is available
                    at <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-impacts/">
                        https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-impacts/</loc> . </bibl>
                <bibl id="exiBestPractices" key="EXI Best Practices"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2007/WD-exi-best-practices-20071219/">
                    <titleref>Efficient XML Interchange (EXI) Best Practices</titleref> , Mike Cokus
                    and Daniel Vogelheim, Editors. World Wide Web Consortium. The latest version is
                    available at <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-best-practices/">
                        https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-best-practices/</loc> . </bibl>
                <bibl id="exiProfile" key="EXI Profile"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2012/WD-exi-profile-20120731/">
                    <titleref>Efficient XML Interchange (EXI) Profile</titleref> , Youenn Fablet and
                    Daniel Peintner, Editors. World Wide Web Consortium. The latest version is
                    available at <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-profile/">
                        https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-profile/</loc> . </bibl>
                <bibl id="xmlSignature" key="XMLDSIG-CORE1"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2013/REC-xmldsig-core1-20130411/">
                    <titleref>XML Signature Syntax and Processing Version 1.1</titleref>, Donald
                    Eastlake Joseph Reagle, David Solo, Frederick Hirsch, Magnus Nystrm, Thomas
                    Roessler, Kelvin Yiu, Editors. Mark Bartel, John Boyer, Barb Fox, Brian
                    LaMacchia, Ed Simon, Authors. World Wide Web Consortium, W3C Recommendation 11
                    April 2013. The latest version is available at <loc
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmldsig-core1/"
                        >https://www.w3.org/TR/xmldsig-core1/</loc>. </bibl>
                <bibl id="charModelFundamentals" key="Character Model Fundamentals"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2005/REC-charmod-20050215/">
                    <titleref>Character Model for the World Wide Web 1.0: Fundamentals </titleref>
                    Martin J. Drst, Franois Yergeau, Richard Ishida, Misha Wolf, Tex Texin,
                    Authors. World Wide Web Consortium, W3C Recommendation 15 February 2005. The
                    latest version is available at <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/charmod/"
                        >https://www.w3.org/TR/charmod/</loc>
                </bibl>
                <bibl id="charModelIdentity" key="Character Model Identity"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2015/WD-charmod-norm-20151119/">
                    <titleref>Character Model for the World Wide Web: String Matching and
                        Searching</titleref> Addison Phillips, Authors. World Wide Web Consortium,
                    W3C Working Draft 19 November 2015. The latest version is available at <loc
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/charmod-norm/"
                        >https://www.w3.org/TR/charmod-norm/</loc>
                </bibl>
                <bibl id="xmlEncryption" key="XMLENC-CORE1"
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2013/REC-xmlenc-core1-20130411/">
                    <titleref>XML Encryption Syntax and Processing Version 1.1</titleref> Donald
                    Eastlake, Joseph Reagle, Frederick Hirsch, Thomas Roessler, Editors. Takeshi
                    Imamura, Blair Dillaway, Ed Simon, Kelvin Yiu, Magnus Nystrm, Authors. World
                    Wide Web Consortium, W3C Recommendation 11 April 2013. The latest version is
                    available at <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlenc-core1/">
                        https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlenc-core1/</loc>. </bibl>
                <bibl key="IETF RFC 2119" href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt" id="RFC2119">
                    <titleref>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</titleref>,
                    S. Bradner, Author. Internet Engineering Task Force, June 1999. Available at
                    http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt. </bibl>

                <bibl key="IETF RFC 3986" href="https://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3986.txt" id="RFC3986">
                    <titleref> Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</titleref>, T.
                    Berners-Lee, R. Fielding, L. Masinter, Authors. Internet Engineering Task Force,
                    January 2005. Available at https://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3986.txt. </bibl>

            </blist>
        </div1>


        <div1 id="canonicalOptionsSchema">
            <head>XML Schema for Canonical EXI Options Document</head>
            <p>The following schema describes the Canonical EXI options document for communicating
                all the Canonical EXI options. It is designed to reuse the <titleref
                    href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#key-optionsDoc">EXI options
                document</titleref>.</p>
            <!-- http://www.freeformatter.com/xml-escape.html -->
            <eg xml:space="preserve">
&lt;xsd:schema targetNamespace=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2016/exi-c14n&quot;
    xmlns:xsd=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema&quot; xmlns:exi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2009/exi&quot;
    elementFormDefault=&quot;qualified&quot;&gt;

    &lt;xsd:import namespace=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2009/exi&quot;
        schemaLocation=&quot;https://www.w3.org/2009/exi/options.xsd&quot;/&gt;

    &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;options&quot;&gt;
        &lt;xsd:complexType&gt;
            &lt;xsd:sequence&gt;
                &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;omitOptionsDocument&quot; minOccurs=&quot;0&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;xsd:complexType/&gt;
                &lt;/xsd:element&gt;
                &lt;xsd:element name=&quot;utcTime&quot; minOccurs=&quot;0&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;xsd:complexType/&gt;
                &lt;/xsd:element&gt;
                &lt;xsd:element ref=&quot;exi:header&quot; minOccurs=&quot;0&quot;/&gt;
            &lt;/xsd:sequence&gt;
        &lt;/xsd:complexType&gt;
    &lt;/xsd:element&gt;

&lt;/xsd:schema&gt;

</eg>

        </div1>

        <inform-div1 id="designDecisions">
            <head>Design Decisions</head>
            <p>This section discusses a number of key decision points in the design of Canonical
                EXI. A rationale for each decision is given and background information is
                provided.</p>


            <div2 id="decisionXml">
                <head>Relationship to XML Security</head>
                <p><loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-c14n">Canonical XML</loc> was designed to be
                    useful to applications that test whether an XML document has been changed (e.g.,
                    XML signature). EXI can be used in such use cases and offers benefits with
                    respect to compact data exchange and fast processing. To ensure that relevant
                    Infoset items are available the following <loc
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#fidelityOptions">EXI Fidelity Options</loc>
                    must be always enabled: <emph>Preserve.pis</emph>,
                        <emph>Preserve.prefixes</emph>, and <emph>Preserve.lexicalValues</emph>.
                    When the XML Canonicalization algorithm preserves comments in a document, the
                    EXI fidelity option <emph>Preserve.comments</emph> must be also enabled (see
                        <loc href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi-best-practices/#signature">here</loc>
                    for more details). </p>
                <p>Canonical EXI, in contrast to Canonical XML, deals with EXI documents and does
                    not require the overhead of plain-text XML data and its associated overhead. </p>
                <p>Both normal forms, Canonical XML and Canonical EXI, can be used for building the
                    normal form of XML Infoset and are applicable in the XML security context.
                    Depending on the application and the associated requirements one or the other
                    may be better suited. For example, XML Signature applications ideally can chose
                    which one fits better.</p>

                <note>
                    <p>In environments that use Canonical EXI for signing and have intermediate
                        nodes that represent the associated Infoset using text XML, it is important
                        to ensure the Canonical EXI signer and validator use the same set of options
                        (see section <specref ref="exchangeCanonicalEXIOptions"/>).</p>
                </note>

                <!--<p><emph>Caution</emph>: The primary objective of Canonical EXI has been to
                    eliminate the associated overhead of plain-text XML when building a canonical
                    form. This means that in the case of signing Canonical XML, EXI can be used on
                    intermediate nodes. On the contrary, it is <emph>not always</emph> possible to
                    use XML on intermediate nodes when Canonical EXI has been used for signing
                    (e.g., superfluous namespace declarations may be deleted).</p>-->

                <!--<p>This document assumes as input a sequence of EXI events. Hence, there is no
                    strong relationship with XML nor with <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-c14n"
                        >Canonical XML</loc>. </p>
                <p>The working group concluded that applications such as XML Signature do not see
                    justifiable benefit from Canonical EXI. Therefore plain-text XML document
                    use-cases should use Canonical XML.</p>-->
            </div2>


            <!--            <div2>
                <head>No EXI Header</head>
                <ednote>
                    <edtext>[DP] REVISIT and check whether this is still true.</edtext>
                </ednote>

                <p> An EXI stream is an <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#header">EXI
                        Header</titleref> followed by an EXI body. </p>
                <p> The EXI Header must not be taken into account when building the canonical EXI
                    form. This strategy ensures that the flexibility in the EXI Header, such as the
                    optional presence of an EXI Cookie, avoids creating different physical
                    representations. </p>
                <p>Therefore the process for building a Canonical EXI stream bases upon the
                    knowledge of the used EXI options. These EXI options must be set or known (e.g.,
                    out-of-band) so that two parties produce the same octet stream. That said,
                    Canonical EXI is solely based upon the <titleref
                        href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#streams">EXI Body stream</titleref>
                </p>
            </div2>-->

            <div2 id="decisionUnicode">
                <head>No Unicode Normalization</head>
                <p>The Unicode standard allows multiple different representations of certain
                    "precomposed characters" (a simple example is "&#231;"). Thus two character
                    sequences that have the same appearance and meaning when printed or displayed
                    may differ in sequences of code points. The W3C provides a reference for
                    interoperable text <bibref ref="charModelFundamentals"/> and also a normalized
                    representation <bibref ref="charModelIdentity"/> but many XML processors do not
                    perform this normalization. Furthermore, applications that must solve this
                    problem can typically enforce character model normalization at all times
                    starting when character content is created in order to avoid processing failures
                    (see <titleref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-c14n#NoCharModelNorm">No Character
                        Model Normalization in Canonical XML</titleref>).
                    <!--EXI Canonicalization uses as its input EXI events in
                    which Strings are represented as sequences of Unicode code points. --></p>
                <p>Therefore, character model normalization is out of scope for EXI canonicalization
                    and a canonical EXI processor must not change the code
                    points.<!-- as it is not allowed to
                    alter any other event. However, character model normalization may become an
                    issue when working with plain-text XML.-->
                </p>
                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>FIX: Check with http://www.w3.org/TR/charmod-norm/</edtext>
                </ednote>-->

                <!-- <ednote>
                    <edtext>WG needs to decide how to deal with such characters. It looks like for
                    XML canonicalization, Unicode normalization is out of scope
                    (http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-c14n#NoCharModelNorm).</edtext>
                    </ednote>-->
            </div2>

            <div2 id="decisionDateTime">
                <head>Date-Time Canonicalization Option</head>
                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>@TODO Fix or remove this section once the utcTime discussion is
                        settled.</edtext>
                </ednote>-->

                <p>XML schema provides a <xspecref
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/#dateTime-canonical-representation"
                        >canonical dateTime representation</xspecref>. That said, the EXI working
                    group (also based on external feedback) has been found that the canonical form
                    for XML Schema dateTime values is defined to make it easy to determine whether
                    two Date-Time values refer to the same instant, regardless of the timezone used. </p>
                <p> On the one hand, for many applications the Date-Time timezone is an important
                    piece of information that should be preserved. As such, it will be surprising if
                    the digital signature is not able to detect changes to this information. In
                    addition, some use cases might be surprised if the canonical EXI format loses
                    all their timezone information and changes all Date-Time values. </p>
                <p>On the other hand, other applications may require the above mentioned canonical
                    form.</p>
                <p>Therefore, dateTime values, by default, are not canonicalized but one may specify
                        <termref def="utcTime">UTC time normalization</termref>.</p>
            </div2>
        </inform-div1>



        <inform-div1 id="examples">
            <head>Canonical EXI Examples</head>

            <div2 id="exampleEventSelection">
                <head>EXI Event Selection</head>
                <p>The subsequently following example depicts the available productions for an
                    example DocContent grammar. From the perspective of the <bibref ref="exiSpec"/>
                    specification it is perfectly fine to match a start element "A" with event code
                    0 (zero) or 4 (four). A canonical EXI form prescribes event code 0 (zero). </p>

                <example>
                    <head>Example productions with event codes</head>

                    <table style="width: 95%;">
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <th colspan="4"/>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <th style="text-align: left;" colspan="3">Syntax</th>
                                <th style="text-align: left;">Event Code</th>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td colspan="3"><emph>DocContent</emph></td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td/>
                                <td>SE ("A") <emph>DocEnd</emph></td>
                                <td>0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td/>
                                <td>SE ("B") <emph>DocEnd</emph></td>
                                <td>1</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td/>
                                <td>SE ("C") <emph>DocEnd</emph></td>
                                <td>2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td/>
                                <td>SE ("D") <emph>DocEnd</emph></td>
                                <td>3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td/>
                                <td>SE(*) <emph>DocEnd</emph></td>
                                <td>4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td/>
                                <td>DT <emph>DocContent</emph></td>
                                <td>5.0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <!-- tr>
                                <td></td>
                                <td></td>
                                <td>CH 
                                <emph>DocContent</emph></td>
                                <td>5.1</td></tr -->
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td/>
                                <td>CM <emph>DocContent</emph></td>
                                <td>5.1.0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td/>
                                <td/>
                                <td>PI <emph>DocContent</emph></td>
                                <td>5.1.1</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </example>

                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>TODO: Add example for Attributes on various levels</edtext>
                </ednote>-->


            </div2>


            <div2 id="exampleStreamOrder">
                <head>Stream Order</head>
                <example>
                    <head>Attribute and Namespace Declaration Sorting</head>
                    <table class="tableBorders" style="padding: 10px;">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th colspan="9" style="text-align: left;">Stream (Event Input
                                    Sequence)</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <!--<td style="text-align: center;" >SC</td>-->
                                <td>SD</td>
                                <td>SE(root)</td>
                                <td>NS(www.foo.com, foo)</td>
                                <td>NS(www.bla.com, bla)</td>
                                <td>AT(c)</td>
                                <td>AT(b)</td>
                                <td>AT(a)</td>
                                <td>EE</td>
                                <td>ED</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <th colspan="9" style="text-align: left;">Canonical EXI Stream</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <!--<td style="text-align: center;" >SC</td>-->
                                <td>SD</td>
                                <td>SE(root)</td>
                                <td>NS(www.bla.com, bla)</td>
                                <td>NS(www.foo.com, foo)</td>
                                <td>AT(a)</td>
                                <td>AT(b)</td>
                                <td>AT(c)</td>
                                <td>EE</td>
                                <td>ED</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>


                    <!--<p>TODO EXI event sequence: SD SE(root) NS(www.foo.com, foo) NS(www.bla.com, bla)
                        AT(c) AT(b) AT(a) EE ED.</p>
                        <p>TODO EXI options: schema-less, ...</p>
                        <p>TODO Canonical EXI event sequence: SD SE(root) NS(www.bla.com, bla)
                        NS(www.foo.com, foo) AT(a) AT(b) AT(c) EE ED.</p>
                        <p>TODO Canonical EXI (octet stream): 00 00 00 00 00</p>-->
                </example>
                <!--<p/>
                    <example>
                    <head>Float Value given as String</head>
                    <p>TODO EXI event sequence: SD SE(float) CH("12.3") EE ED.</p>
                    <p>TODO EXI options: schema-informed, element float types as Float</p>
                    <p>TODO Canonical EXI (octet stream)</p>
                    </example>-->
            </div2>

            <div2 id="exampleFloat">
                <head>EXI Floats</head>
                <p>The Float datatype representation can be converted to the canonical form going
                    through the following steps. Note, implementations are free to choose any
                    strategy as long as the constraints in <specref ref="dt-float"/> are met.</p>
                <example>
                    <head>An algorithm for converting float values to the canonical form</head>
                    <p>Let the float value have a decimal notation of the form
                            <code>&lt;before&gt;.&lt;after&gt;</code> where <code>before</code>
                        represents the value before the decimal point and <code>after</code>
                        represents the value after the decimal point. The canonical representation
                        of the mantissa and exponent shall be determined as follows:</p>
                    <olist>
                        <!-- #1 -->
                        <item>
                            <p>Initialize the exponent with the value 0 (zero).
                                <!--Jump to step 2.--></p>
                        </item>
                        <!-- #2 -->
                        <item>
                            <p>Examine the float value and extract the two portions before and after
                                the decimal point. If the value after the decimal point can be
                                represented as 0 (zero) without losing precision, then jump to step
                                4, otherwise jump to step 3. </p>
                        </item>
                        <!-- #3 -->
                        <item>
                            <p>Decrement the exponent by 1 (one) and shift the decimal point of the
                                float value by one digit to the right. Jump back to step 2.</p>
                        </item>
                        <!-- #4 -->
                        <item>
                            <p>The portion before the decimal point can be safely converted to the
                                signed mantissa value. <!--Jump to step 5.--></p>
                        </item>
                        <!-- #5 -->
                        <item>
                            <p>If the signed mantissa is unequal 0 (zero), unequal -0 (negative
                                zero), and contains a trailing zero, then jump to 6, otherwise jump
                                to step 7.</p>
                        </item>
                        <!-- #6 -->
                        <item>
                            <p>Increment the exponent by 1 (one) and shift the mantissa by one digit
                                to the right. Jump back to 5.</p>
                        </item>
                        <!-- #7 -->
                        <item>
                            <p>If the mantissa is equal -0 set the mantissa value to 0 (zero).
                                Finished.</p>
                        </item>
                    </olist>
                </example>



                <p>The subsequently following examples depict possible float values opposed to their
                    canonical form.</p>
                <example>
                    <head>Canonicalized EXI Float values</head>
                    <!--<p>The normalized EXI representation of 123,012300 is given by the mantissa
                        value 1230123 and the exponent value -4.</p>
                        <p> The canonical representation for 0.0 is given by the mantissa value 0
                        and the exponent value 0.</p>
                        <p>The float value 1,0 is represented by the mantissa value 1 and the
                        exponent value 0</p>
                        <p> -1230,01 is represented by the mantissa value -123001 and the exponent
                        value -2</p>
                        <p> 0,1230 is represented by the mantissa value 123 and the exponent value
                        -3</p>
                        <p> 12300 is represented by the mantissa value 123 and the exponent value
                        +2</p>-->
                    <!--<p> 12300 is represented by the mantissa value 12300 and the exponent value
                        0</p>-->



                    <table style="width: 75%;">
                        <!-- width="95%" -->
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <th style="text-align: left;" colspan="1">Float Value</th>
                                <th/>
                                <th colspan="2" style="text-align: left;">Canonical EXI Float Value
                                </th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <th colspan="2"/>
                                <th style="text-align: left;">Mantissa</th>
                                <th style="text-align: left;">Exponent</th>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td>123.012300</td>
                                <th rowspan="10"> &#8658; </th>
                                <td>1230123</td>
                                <td>-4</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>0.0</td>
                                <td>0</td>
                                <td>0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>-0.0</td>
                                <td>0</td>
                                <td>0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>1.0</td>
                                <td>1</td>
                                <td>0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>-1230.01</td>
                                <td>-123001</td>
                                <td>-2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>0.1230</td>
                                <td>123</td>
                                <td>-3</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>12300</td>
                                <td>123</td>
                                <td>2</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>12.0</td>
                                <td>12</td>
                                <td>0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>120E-1</td>
                                <td>12</td>
                                <td>0</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>1.2E1</td>
                                <td>12</td>
                                <td>0</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </example>

                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>#1: Is there any strong reason why we should also shift to the
                    right. For example 12300 could be represented more efficiently as
                    123E+2. </edtext>
                    </ednote>-->
                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>How does this approach work for databinding layers or IEEE floats
                    with undefinite digits after the decimal point. Idea: Add abort criteria
                    - shift left until mantissa exceeds 2147483648 (see
                    http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#encodingUnsignedInteger) or float range -
                    (2^63) to 2^63-1. </edtext>
                    </ednote>-->



                <!-- The decimal place number has to be normalized such that there is 
                    a single digit which is non-zero to the right unless the decimal place value 
                    being represented is zero. E.g., 123.12300 is normalized to 123.123. The 
                    canonical representation of the mantissa and exponent is determined as following: 
                    The float value must be normalized that there is a single digit which is 
                    non-zero to the left of the floating point and at least a single digit to 
                    the right of the decimal point unless the value being represented is zero. 
                    The canonical representation the exponent must be indicated by "E". Leading 
                    zeroes and the preceding optional "+" sign are prohibited in the exponent. 
                    If the exponent is zero, it must be indicated by "0". For the mantissa, the 
                    preceding optional "+" sign as well as the decimal point is prohibited. Leading 
                    and trailing zeroes are prohibited subject to the following: number representations 
                    must be normalized such that there is a single digit which is non-zero to 
                    the left of the decimal point and at least a single digit to the right of 
                    the decimal point unless the value being represented is zero. The canonical 
                    representation for zero is 0E0. -->
            </div2>
            <div2 id="exampleDateTime">
                <head>EXI Date-Times</head>
                <p>The subsequently following examples depict possible date-Time values opposed to their
                    canonical form. The canonical EXI form always retains the original seconds part.</p>  
                <example>
                    <head>Canonicalized EXI Date-Time values</head>
                <table style="width: 75%;">
                    <!-- width="95%" -->
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th style="text-align: left;">Date-Time Value</th>
			    <th />
                            <th colspan="3" style="text-align: left;">Canonical EXI Date-Time Value 
                            </th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <th colspan="2"/>
                            <th style="text-align: left;">(utcTime==false)</th>
                            <th />
                            <th>(utcTime==true)</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>2015-08-11T24:00:00-07:30</td>
                            <th rowspan="2"> &#8658; </th>
                            <td>2015-08-12T00:00:00-07:30</td>
                            <th rowspan="2"> &#8658; </th>
                            <td>2015-08-12T07:30:00Z</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>2012-06-30T23:59:60-06:00</td>
                            <td>2012-06-30T23:59:60-06:00</td>
                            <td>2012-07-01T05:59:60Z</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
                </example>
            </div2>
        </inform-div1>




        <inform-div1 id="exiApplications">
            <head>Canonical EXI Applications</head>
            <!--            <div2 id="canonicalizationMethod">
                <head>Canonicalization Method</head>
                <p>EXI Canonicalization may be used as a canonicalization method algorithm in XML
                    Signature <bibref ref="xmlSignature"/> and XML Encryption <bibref
                        ref="xmlEncryption"/>. The identifier
                    <code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n</code> hereby specifies the rules of
                    this document.</p>
            </div2>-->
            <div2 id="signatureProcessingSteps">
                <head>Signature Processing Steps</head>
                <p>The figure below describes the involved processing steps when Canonical EXI is
                    used for signing an EXI document or a fragment and the signature value is
                    embedded within the document: First, the EXI stream or fragment of the EXI
                    stream to be signed has to be transformed in a canonical form according to the
                    requirements given in this document (see <specref ref="canonicalEXI"/>). Then,
                    the canonical representation is used to determine the signature value based on
                    the intended signature algorithm. At this point the signature value can be set
                    within the EXI document and can be transmitted to the recipient. </p>

                <p> To validate the signature value for compliance, the receiver has to build the
                    canonical EXI stream for the signed portion. Note, this step can be skipped if
                    there is pre-knowledge on the receiver side that the EXI stream already fulfills
                    the requirements of Canonical EXI. Finally, to determine the correctness of the
                    signature value (based on the signature algorithm) it can be compared with the
                    embedded signature value provided by the sender.</p>

                <graphic source="CanonicalEXI.png" alt="Canonical EXI used in Signature"
                    id="figSignatureSteps"/>

                <p>In the case of XML Signature processing, a detached signature can be used or an
                    enveloped signature, in which case the signature element is not included in the
                    hash calculation.</p>

                <!--            </div2>

            <div2 id="signatureGeneration">
                <head>Signature Generation</head>-->
                <!--<ednote>
                    <edtext>This section is meant to outline ideas and may be revised in a future
                        version. Feedback and comments are welcome! </edtext>
                </ednote>-->

                <p>During signature generation, the digest is computed over the canonical EXI
                    stream. There are two independent aspects that are to be solved. </p>

                <olist>
                    <item>
                        <p><emph>What gets hashed</emph>, and <!--: the Canonical EXI stream-->
                            <!--The working group tends to recommend that
                            the hash is generated for the Canonical EXI stream taking also into
                            account the EXI options.-->
                        </p>
                        <!--<ednote>
                            <name>Issue Canonical EXI options</name>
                            <edtext>The working group may need to elaborate a canonical form for the
                                EXI options.</edtext>
                        </ednote>
                        <ednote>
                            <name>Warning</name>
                            <edtext>One issue in that regard is the schemaId in EXI. The EXI
                                specification does not dictate the syntax or semantics of this
                                field. Hence applications need to take care of the appropriate use.
                            </edtext>
                        </ednote>-->
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p><emph>How to exchange and share Canonical EXI options (other than
                                out-of-band) <!--as part of the EXI stream--></emph> (see <specref
                                ref="exchangeCanonicalEXIOptions"
                            />)<!--: The
                            canonicalization process of EXI bases upon the knowledge of the used
                                <loc
                                href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#options
                                "
                                >EXI options</loc> which is an optional part of the EXI header.
                            These options communicate the various EXI options that have been used to
                            encode the actual XML information with EXI and are crucial to be known
                            (Appendix <specref ref="exchangeEXIOptions"/> provides some best
                            practices).--></p>
                    </item>
                </olist>

            </div2>




            <div2 id="exchangeCanonicalEXIOptions">
                <head>Exchange Canonical EXI Options (Best Practices)</head>

                <p> The canonicalization process of EXI is based on the knowledge of the used
                        <specref ref="canonicalOptions"/> which imply the <loc
                        href="https://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#options
                        ">EXI
                        options</loc>. The Canonical EXI options specify whether the EXI Options
                    document is omitted and whether a Date-Time values must be represented using
                    Coordinated Universal Time (UTC). Also, the EXI options part (which in its
                    entirety might be optional in the EXI header) communicate the various options
                    that have been used to encode the actual XML information with EXI and are
                    essential for any EXI processor. <!--Given that the presence of <loc
                        href="http://www.w3.org/TR/exi/#options">EXI options</loc> in its entirety
                    might be optional in the EXI header,-->
                    <!--The following subsections provide and discuss best practices how to exchange
                    them - so that for example such practices can be successfully used as part of
                    the digital signature framework or in other use-cases.-->
                    <!--Different options are discussed below.--></p>

                <!--<p>
                    It is important to facilitate sharing EXI Options with the canonical form - so that
                    for example it can be succesfully used as part of the digital signature framework or
                    in other use-cases. Currently different options are discussed. </p>-->

                <p>Appendix <specref ref="canonicalOptionsSchema"/> provides an XML Schema
                    describing the Canonical EXI Options document. Specifically, it allows users to
                    communicate EXI-C14N (and EXI) options as part of the digital signature
                    framework, via an out-of-band protocol, an overarching specification, or in
                    other use-cases.</p>


                <div3>
                    <head>Example - XML Signature</head>
                    <p> According to section 6.1 of <loc
                            href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmldsig-core1/#sec-AlgID">XML Signature
                            Syntax and Processing Version</loc> explicit additional parameters to an
                        algorithm appear as content elements within the algorithm role element. The
                        role element in this case is "CanonicalizationMethod". Hence, Canonical EXI
                        use cases can leverage the sub-elements in CanonicalizationMethod. </p>
                    <p>CanonicalizationMethod element is given a schema type as: </p>
                    <eg xml:space="preserve">
    &lt;element name=&quot;CanonicalizationMethod&quot; type=&quot;ds:CanonicalizationMethodType&quot;/&gt; 
    
    &lt;complexType name=&quot;CanonicalizationMethodType&quot; mixed=&quot;true&quot;&gt;
        &lt;sequence&gt;
            &lt;any namespace=&quot;##any&quot; minOccurs=&quot;0&quot; maxOccurs=&quot;unbounded&quot;/&gt;
            &lt;!-- (0,unbounded) elements from (1,1) namespace --&gt;
        &lt;/sequence&gt;
        &lt;attribute name=&quot;Algorithm&quot; type=&quot;anyURI&quot; use=&quot;required&quot;/&gt; 
    &lt;/complexType&gt;
                    </eg>

                    <p>A possible Canonical EXI options document (as part of XML Signature) may look
                        as follows</p>

                    <eg xml:space="preserve">
...
&lt;CanonicalizationMethod xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/09/xmldsig#&quot; 
    Algorithm=&quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n&quot;&gt;
    &lt;exi-c14n:options xmlns:exi=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2009/exi&quot;
        xmlns:exi-c14n=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2016/exi-c14n&quot;&gt;
        &lt;exi-c14n:omitOptionsDocument/&gt;
        &lt;exi-c14n:utcTime/&gt;
        &lt;exi:header&gt;
            &lt;exi:common&gt;
                &lt;exi:compression/&gt;
                &lt;exi:fragment/&gt;
            &lt;/exi:common&gt;
        &lt;/exi:header&gt;
    &lt;/exi-c14n:options&gt;
&lt;/CanonicalizationMethod&gt; 
...
                    </eg>

                    <note>
                        <p>Another proposal is to use the <loc
                                href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmldsig-core1/#sec-SignatureProperties"
                                >SignatureProperties</loc> element.</p>
                    </note>

                    <!--<p>The <emph>advantages</emph> of this kind of approach are that EXI options are </p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>easily integrated within digital signature</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>represented as plain-text XML (no need of an EXI options decoder)</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>

                    <p>The <emph>disadvantages</emph> of this kind of approach are that EXI
                        options</p>

                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>cannot be easily used in scenarios where no digital signature
                                framework is used</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>-->

                </div3>

                <!--<div3>
                    <head>Option 2 - URI scheme fragment identifier</head>
                    <ednote>
                        <edtext>The working group looks for strong use-cases to keep this best
                            practice</edtext>
                    </ednote>

                    <p>In general the identifier
                            <code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n#WithoutEXIOptions</code> specifies
                        the use of Canonical EXI without EXI Options document. Additionally a
                        fragment identifier could be used to uniquely refer to a specific set of
                        options (e.g., <code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n#AB1235</code>). One
                        possibility is to make up some URI schema for the EXI options. Another
                        possibility is to encode the EXI options element as EXI stream and map it to
                        binary (e.g., hexBinary). For the latter it is important to make sure that
                        one set of options maps to exactly one fragment identifier (e.g., see
                            <specref ref="canonicalHeader"/>).
                    </p>

                    <p>The <emph>advantages</emph> of this kind of approach are that EXI options are </p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>Closely coupled with canonicalization method algorithm</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>It is very efficient and short</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Can be used in many scenarios where no digital signature framework is
                                used</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>

                    <p>The <emph>disadvantage</emph> of this kind of approach is that it </p>

                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>demands retrieving EXI options required to decode the fragment
                                identifier (byte array?) with an EXI processor</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>
                </div3>-->

                <!--<div3>
                    <head>Option 3 - EXI options within EXI stream </head>
                    <ednote>
                        <edtext>The working group wonders whether this is still a best practice
                            given that it cannot comminicate whether utcTime normalization needs to
                            take place nor whether the EXI options document needs to be
                            present</edtext>
                    </ednote>
                    <p>For the sake of completeness, it is possible that the EXI options are present
                        in the EXI stream itself (see identifier
                            <code>http://www.w3.org/TR/exi-c14n</code>).</p>

                    <p>The <emph>advantages</emph> of this kind of approach are that EXI options are </p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>Closely coupled with the EXI stream</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>It is very efficient and EXI processors can already deal with it</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Can be used in many scenarios where no digital signature framework is
                                used</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>

                    <p>The <emph>disadvantage</emph> of this kind of approach is that it </p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>seems to be an undesirable overhead (e.g., size) for many use cases
                                to require EXI options to be present all the time.</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>

                </div3>-->

                <div3>
                    <head>Decision Criteria</head>
                    <p>This section provided best practices how to exchange Canonical EXI options
                        but use-cases are not limited to the afore mentioned proposals. There might
                        be other methods for communicating Canonical EXI options:</p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>A community of interest might decide on a set of Canonical EXI
                                options that are appropriate for their use case and codify them in
                                their specifications / standards. Implementations that comply with
                                these specifications / standards will all use the same options,
                                without the need for communicating them dynamically at runtime.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>A community of interest may devise a protocol for exchanging the
                                Canonical EXI options dynamically out-of-band as needed.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p><emph>and so forth</emph></p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>
                </div3>

            </div2>


        </inform-div1>

        <inform-div1 id="useful-reference">
            <head>Useful References</head>
            <glist>
                <gitem>
                    <label>RFC 3986</label>
                    <def>
                        <p>Normalization and comparison of url and uri values, if applied within a
                            document, is best performed in accordance with <bibref ref="RFC3986"
                            />.</p>
                    </def>
                </gitem>
            </glist>

        </inform-div1>



        <inform-div1 id="changes">
            <head>Recent Specification Changes</head>
            <div2>
                <head>Changes from Candidate Recommendation</head>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Clarifications added on how to canonicalize dateTime values,
							if the Canonical EXI Option <termref def="utcTime">utcTime</termref>
                            is equal to <code>true</code> (see <specref ref="dt-dateTime"/>):
							<ulist>
								<item>by applying the algorithm defined in
									<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#adding-durations-to-dateTimes">
										adding durations to dateTimes</titleref> <bibref ref="schemaDatatypes2"/>
								</item>
								<item>by not modifying the value of seconds
								</item>
							</ulist>
						</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Added note describing in which cases extraneous events are still required (see <specref ref="excludeExtraneousEvents"/>)</p> 
                    </item>
                </ulist>
            </div2>
			<div2>
                <head>Changes from Last Call Working Draft</head>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Updated the section on motivation to make clear that EXI canonicalization
                            is useful for traditional XML users also (see <specref ref="motivation"
                            />).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Introduced the concept of Canonical EXI Options to provide a single,
                            simple, unambiguous way to express the rules of EXI-C14N options (see
                                <specref ref="canonicalOptions"/>).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>The Canonical EXI Option <termref def="omitOptionsDocument"
                                >omitOptionsDocument</termref> specifies whether the fifth part of
                            the EXI Header, the EXI Options, is present (see <specref
                                ref="canonicalHeader"/>).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Changed the presence of the element schemaId in the Canonical EXI Header
                            from "MUST" to "MAY" by describing the consequences in an accompanying
                            warning (see <specref ref="canonicalHeader"/>).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>It was made clear that the element datatypeRepresentationMap must be
                            omitted when the value of the Preserve.lexicalValues fidelity option is
                            true (see <specref ref="canonicalHeader"/>).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>It is now explicitly stated that each event in an EXI stream participates
                            in a mapping system that relates events to XML Information Items (see
                                <specref ref="canonicalBody"/>).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>In the process of selecting the EXI event that matches most precisely
                            Character (CH) events have been added (see <specref
                                ref="exiEventMatching"/>).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>A section about EXI content handling specifices how to deal with
                            extraneous events, empty element content, and whitespaces (see <specref
                                ref="exiContentHandling"/>).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Added further constraints for Date-Time values. Moreover, the Canonical
                            EXI Option <termref def="utcTime">utcTime</termref> specifies whether
                            Date-Time values must be represented using Coordinated Universal Time
                            (see <specref ref="dt-dateTime"/>).</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
            </div2>
        </inform-div1>

        <inform-div1 id="acknowledgements">
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>

            <p>This document is the work of the <loc href="https://www.w3.org/XML/EXI/">Efficient XML
                    Interchange (EXI) WG</loc>.</p>

            <p>Members of the Working Group are (at the time of writing, sorted alphabetically by
                last name): </p>
            <ulist>
                <item>
                    <p>Carine Bournez, W3C/ERCIM (<emph>staff contact</emph>)</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Don Brutzman, Web3D Consortium</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Michael Cokus, MITRE Corporation</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Fernndez, Javier D., Vienna University of Economics and Business</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Joerg Heuer, Siemens AG</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Schloss Nathan, Facebook</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Sebastian K&#228;bisch, Siemens AG</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Takuki Kamiya, Fujitsu Laboratories of America (<emph>chair</emph>)</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Richard Kuntschke, Siemens AG</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Don McGregor, Web3D Consortium</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Daniel Peintner, Siemens AG</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Matsukura Ryuichi, Fujitsu Laboratories</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Liam Quin, W3C/MIT (<emph>staff contact</emph>)</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Mohamed Zergaoui, INNOVIMAX</p>
                </item>
            </ulist>
            <p>The EXI Working Group would like to acknowledge the following former members or
                external experts for their leadership, guidance and expertise they provided
                throughout the process of creating this document (sorted alphabetically by last
                name): <!--individual tenure in the WG. (sorted in chronologically) --></p>
            <ulist>
                <item>
                    <p>John Cowan</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Yusuke Doi</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Youenn Fablet</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Bruce Hill </p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Frederick Hirsch</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Rumen Kyusakov</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>David Lee</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Rich Rollman</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>John Schneider</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Josh Soref</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <p>Alessandro Triglia</p>
                </item>
            </ulist>
        </inform-div1>

    </back>
</spec>
